Finding Aid for George Kish papers 1932-1989
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
George Kish papers 1932-1989, 1955-1980
Kish, George, 1914-
10.5 linear feet
Professor of geography at the University of Michigan. Series include correspondence, subject files, professional societies, geography courses, reprints, manuscripts, notes as a student, and photographs; files relate to his professional interests and to the subject of geography.
90123 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
Donated by his wife, Dr. Elvina A. Kish, M.D. (Donor No. 7703 ), August 1989.
The collection is open for research.
George Kish was an internationally acclaimed professor of geography at the University of Michigan, where he served for over fifty years. He was born in Budapest, Hungary in 1914. His education began in Hungary where he graduated from secondary school summa cum laude and won the national competition in geography. He then moved to Paris, where he studied political science, geography, and history, the latter two at the Sorbonne. Returning to Hungary, he received both a M.S. in Economics in 1938 and a D.Sc. in Geography in 1939 at the University of Budapest.
Kish came to America in 1939 to continue his studies in geography at the University of Michigan, where he received his Ph.D. in 1945. During the Second World War, he acted as a translator of Hungarian newspapers for the Office of Strategic Services. After the war, he returned to the U-M where he remained for fifty years, beginning as a research assistant and moving to full professor in 1956. In between, he was a teaching fellow (1940-1943) and map curator at the Clements Library (1944-1946). Originally his last name was spelled "Kiss," but on becoming a United State citizen in the late 1940s, it was Americanized to "Kish," to reflect its accurate pronunciation in Hungarian. Kish gained international acclaim as a geographer and was an active participant in his profession, especially in the subfield of political geography.
As an expert in his field, Kish was sought out for visiting positions by other institutions, including Northwestern University, Oxford University, London School of Economics, University of Warsaw, and the University of Tel-Aviv. Awarded Fulbrights in the early 1950s and mid-1960s, he taught in Italy both times. In 1980, he was named the Kenneth Nebenzahl, Jr. Lecturer in the History of Cartography at the Newberry Library in Chicago.
Kish was active in professional societies and organizations, such as the Association of American Geographers and the International Geographical Union (IGU). In the IGU, he served as chairperson for many of its committees and commissions, such as the United States National Committee and the Commission on Old Maps. He also helped found the Commission on the History of Geographical Thought for the IGU. Kish was also a member of the American Association for the Advancement of Slavic Studies and served on its board of directors during the 1960s.
Besides holding various visiting professorships, he traveled the world over to conduct research for his many books and articles. To learn more about the noted Swedish explorers A. E. Nordenskiold and Sven Hedin, he traveled to Sweden to examine records of their lives. While there, he received two prestigious awards: the Andree Medal for Polar Studies from the Swedish Geographical Society and the Linnaeus Medal for Studies in the History of Science from the Royal Swedish Academy of Science. Kish's books and articles were published in many languages and printed in journals around the world.
Kish was also active closer to home. He supported his home university and participated in the life of the University of Michigan. In 1975, he received the honor of being named to give the Henry Russel Lecture. In 1981, Kish became the William Herbert Hobbs professor of Geography after the Geography Department was discontinued in that year. He took an interest in university life and was on several University Senate committees, including the College of Literature, Sciences, and Arts Library Committee. He was president of the Ann Arbor Symphony Orchestra from 1972 to 1974 and president of the Michigan Orchestra Association from 1977 to 1979. He was also president of the Michigan Map Society in 1983 and 1984.
Kish married Elvina Anger, M.D., in 1949, a union that brought forth one daughter. Kish made his home in Ann Arbor for the last fifty years of his life and continued teaching at the university, following his retirement in 1984, until his death in July 1989.
The George Kish papers are divided into eight series: Correspondence, Subject Folders, Professional Societies, Geography Courses, Reprints, Manuscripts, Notes as a Student, and Photographs. These eight sections correspond, more or less, to the order that Kish maintained for his own files. The collection documents the academic career of Kish, from his Paris days as a student and his years at the U-M as a professor to his retirement and beyond. The collection's focus is not strictly on the university, as it also reflects Kish's prolific writings and his work in professional societies.
Subjects:
American Geographical Union.; Association of American Geographers.; Geography.; International Geographical Union.; Kish, George, 1914-1989; University of Michigan. Dept. of Geography.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Geography.; Henry Russel Award (University of Michigan); Italy.; Map making--History.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre/Form:
Photographs.
- Correspondence
  Correspondence covers a fifty-year span from 1939 to 1989, a period during which Kish was usually at the University of Michigan. The files are arranged as Kish had them, first by groups of years, then, within each group, alphabetically. For example, the folders for 1961 to 1966 are comprised of an alphabetical run of correspondence for those six years. Throughout the correspondence there are letters in the many languages in which Kish communicated. These include (in order of frequency): English, Italian, French, German, Swedish, Hungarian, Spanish, and Russian. This section is mostly general correspondence from both individuals and organizations.
  - Pre-1940 1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940-1948 A through Z, 23 folders (Box 1)
  - 1949-1953 A through Z, 23 folders (Box 1)
  - 1954-1957
    - A through H, 9 folders (Box 1)
    - I through Z, 13 folders (Box 2)
  - 1958-1960
    - A through T, 20 folders (Box 2)
    - U through Z, 4 folders (Box 3)
  - 1961-1966 A through Z, 27 folders (Box 3)
  - 1967-1972
    - A through H, 9 folders (Box 3)
    - I through Z, 14 folders (Box 4)
  - 1973-1983 A through Z, 24 folders (Box 4)
  - 1981-1989 A through Z, 23 folders (Box 5)
- Subject Files
  Subject Files contains both correspondence and other materials ordered into one alphabetical sequence. Subjects covered in this section include conferences (documenting Kish's involvement in the planning of and his attendance at), correspondence with publishers, and other topics. Under the sub-heading "Personal," some of Kish's private life is revealed, especially his becoming a United States citizen and his retirement from the U-M. While Kish was in Sweden conducting research for his biography of A. E. Nordenskiold, his secretary kept fairly complete records for him of events in Ann Arbor. This is found in the "Sweden to Ann Arbor Office" folder. Both Kish's life and interests can be glimpsed by glancing through the headings of the Subject Folders.
  - American Association for the Advancement of Slavic Studies 1962-1968 (Box 5)
  - American Council of Learned Societies 1963, 1979, 1984 (Box 5)
  - Arms Control Seminar 1961 (Box 5)
  - Bentley Library 1982 (Box 5)
  - Berlin 1979-1980
    - Wolfenbuettel 1978-1979 (Box 5)
  - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutes/"Dialogue de Civilizations" conference 1973 (Box 5)
  - Center for the History of European Expansion in America 1966 (Box 5)
  - Center for Russian and East European Studies 1974, 1983-1986 (Box 5)
  - Class Schedules 1942-1944 (Box 5)
  - Conference board of Associated Councils 1963-1964 (Box 5)
  - Cosmos Travel Bureau/Intourist 1956-1957 (Box 5)
  - Department of State-Foreign Service Institute 1962-1963 (Box 5)
  - Detroit-1985 1983-1988 (Box 5)
  - Dictionary of Art 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - Economic Atlas of the Soviet Union 1959-1960
    - Reviews 1960-1961 (Box 5)
  - Educational Television and Radio Center, Ann Arbor 1955-1956 (Box 5)
  - Encyclopedia of the U.S.S.R. 1947-1948 (Box 5)
  - European Economic Community 1962-1965 (Box 5)
  - Ford Foundation 1958-1961, 1964 (Box 5)
  - Fulbright Fellowship Materials 1949-1953 (Box 5)
  - Fulbright-1963 1963-1965
    - Italy 1961-1965 (Box 5)
  - Geography Department 1963-1965 (Box 5)
  - "Geography: A Profitable Tool for the Business Executive", no date (Box 5)
  - "Golden Temple" 1975-1977 (Box 5)
  - History of Discoveries, Society of 1967, 1971-1977, 1982 (Box 5)
  - History of Geography 1979-1983 (Box 5)
  - Imago Mundi
    - 1947-1953 (Box 5)
    - 1954-1960 (Box 5)
    - 1961-1964 (Box 5)
    - 1966-1986 (Box 5)
  - International Geographers Union/National Academy of the Sciences-regarding trip to Russia 1973-1977 (Box 6)
  - Israel-University of Tel Aviv 1969-1971, 1973-1974 (Box 6)
  - Italian Geographers Congress 1983 (Box 6)
  - Italy-1960 1959-1960 (Box 6)
  - LS&A-Library Commission 1979-1982 (Box 6)
  - Maps and the Columbian Encounter-Exhibition, Kish, advisor 1987-1988 (Box 6)
  - Marzoli, Carla-Correspondence 1976-1987 (Box 6)
  - Massachusetts Institute of Technology-Center for International Studies 1953 (Box 6)
  - Monumenta Cartographia Vetustoris Aevi/International Geographers Union-Commission for Early Maps 1961-1982, 4 folders (Box 6)
  - National Geographic Society 1983-1989 (Box 6)
  - National Research Council
    - Correspondence 1948-1951 (Box 6)
    - Circulars 1948-1950 (Box 6)
  - National Science Foundation 1961-1968 (Box 6)
  - Naval War College, Newport, RI 1958-1962 (Box 6)
  - Newberry Library, Chicago
    - Creation of a Center for the History of Cartography 1966-1971 (Box 6)
    - Herman Dunlap Smith Center for Cartography 1972-1983 (Box 6)
  - "Nordenskiold, A. E.: A Critical Biography"
    - Correspondence and details 1965-1973 (Box 6)
    - Lecture and publication 1968 (Box 6)
  - Office of Naval Research-Correspondence and details of research projects 1958-1967 (Box 6)
  - Office of Strategic Services
    - Office of Volunteer Readings
      - Incoming correspondence 1943-1945 (Box 6)
      - Outgoing correspondence 1942-1945 (Box 6)
    - Summaries of Hungarian Newspapers 1943-1945 (Box 6)
  - Organization for European Economic Cooperation-Electricity Section (Box 6)
  - Pacific Science Conference, Tenth 1961-1962 (Box 6)
  - Paris-1984 1981-1984 (Box 6)
  - Paris-1987 1987 (Box 6)
  - Personal
    - Autobiography, Vitae, and List of Articles (Box 6)
    - Immigration and Naturalization 1939-1943, 1947-1948 (Box 6)
    - Visa Correspondence 1948 (Box 6)
    - Retirement Party 1984
      - Letters of Congratulations 1984 (Box 6)
    - Scio Township Rezoning/Chrysler Case 1970 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous 1948, 1965, 1985 (Box 6)
  - Peruvian Congress of Geography 1961 (Box 6)
  - Pisa-1981 Ninth International Conference on Cartography 1976-1981 (Box 6)
  - Publishers and Presses
    - Artist and Writer's Press 1963-1965 (Box 6)
    - Astrolabe/Editions Raymond Chabaud 1987-1989 (Box 6)
    - Astrolabe-"La vie de Sven Hedin" 1988 (Box 6)
    - University of Michigan Press 1962-1972, 1981-1984, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Research Grants/Descriptions of selected studies 1945-1977 (Box 6)
  - Russel Lectures 1985-1986 (Box 6)
  - Russel, J. A.-Correspondence 1976 (Box 6)
  - Russian Studies, Center for 1961-1965 (Box 6)
  - Second International Reunion of the History of the Art of Navigation and of Hydrography (Brazil, 1976) 1976 (Box 6)
  - Society of the Azazels 1932, 1975-1987 (Box 6)
  - Sven Hedin biography-Correspondence 1974-1983 (Box 6)
  - Sweden to Ann Arbor Office-Kish Correspondence 1968 (Box 7)
  - Sweden 1973-1976 (Box 7)
  - Tennessee Valley Authority/Reclamation Acts 1944-1953 (Box 7)
  - United Nations University 1981-1983, 1987-1988 (Box 7)
  - United States/Italy Seminar in Geography
    - Correspondence 1976-1980 (Box 7)
    - Notes and Proposals 1976-1980 (Box 7)
  - University Lecture Committee 1961-1962 (Box 7)
  - "University of Michigan File-G. Kish" 1967-1979, 1984-1985 (Box 7)
  - Vatican 1978, 1985-1988 (Box 7)
  - "War" 1943-1945 (Box 7)
  - World Geography
    - Correspondence with contributors 1949-1956, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous 1951 (Box 7)
- Professional Societies
  In the Professional Societies series, the researcher will find documentation about Kish's involvement with the Association of American Geographers (AAG), the American Geographical Union (AGU), and International Geographical Union (IGU). The most extensive records are for the AAG and several of its committees on which Kish served. Kish was a regular contributor to the AGU's Geographical Review. Documented here are his relations with AGU editors, while his contributions will be found in the Reprints series.
  - Association of American Geographers
    - Correspondence 1946-1988, 5 folders (Box 7)
    - Cartography Committee 1954-1957 (Box 7)
    - Commission on College Geography 1965-1967
      - "Geopacks" 1965-1967 (Box 7)
    - Committee on Exchange 1954-1957 (Box 7)
    - Committee on Humanities 1963-1965 (Box 7)
    - Committee on Relations with Foreign Geographers 1949-1951, 1954-1957, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - East Lakes Division 1980-1982 (Box 7)
    - Eastern European Committee
      - Correspondence 1966, 1973-1976 (Box 7)
      - Newsletter and Report 1971, 1973, 1975 (Box 7)
    - Great Lakes Chapter 1954-1957 (Box 7)
    - Peace Research 1964-1966 (Box 7)
    - Political Geographers 1954-1957 (Box 7)
    - Program Committee for 1957, 1956 (Box 7)
    - Soviet Geography Committee 1954-1957 (Box 7)
    - Soviet Geographers Exchange 1962-1963 (Box 7)
    - Visiting Scientist 1985 (Box 7)
  - American Geographical Society-Correspondence (with editors of the Geographical Review) 1940-1985, 5 folders (Box 7)
  - International Geographical Union
    - Correspondence 1973, 1979, 1985-1989, 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Committee on History of Geographical Thought
      - Correspondence 1969-1971 (Box 7)
      - Sixth Conference September 1975, 1974-1975 (Box 7)
    - Rio de Janeiro Conference 1956 (Box 8)
    - United States National Committee
      - Minutes and Constitution 1959-1965 (Box 8)
      - Minutes 1966-1972 (Box 8)
- Geography Courses 1940-1988
  Kish was considered a good teacher by his students, and in the Geography Courses series, his teaching methods are documented. The course files are ordered by course number, with preference given to the most recent number, if known. These materials include both master-copies of exams and lecture notes. Some bibliographies and source-books are also included. There are also some courses where only the title or subject matter is known and these are at the end of the section in alphabetical order.
  - Geography 100 (Geog. I) 1940-1943 (Box 8)
  - Geog. 101 (Geog II, Introduction to Geography) 1941-1949, 1977, 1981, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Geog. 411 (112)
    - Exams and Projects 1947-1983 (Box 8)
    - Exams 1988 (Box 8)
  - Geog. 412 (121-122) 1951-1983 (Box 8)
  - Geog. 415 (116, Geography of Europe)
    - Lecture Notes, no date (Box 8)
    - Exams 1947-1989 (Box 8)
  - Geog. 435 (135)
    - Lecture Notes 1941 (Box 8)
    - Exams 1941-1982 (Box 8)
  - F.S.I. Europe Lecture Notes, no date (Box 8)
  - Geography of the Soviet Union I 1960s (Box 8)
  - History of Cartography 1972 (Box 8)
  - Russian Studies/Interdepartmental Studies 1961-1962 (Box 8)
  - U.S.S.R. Lecture Notes, no date (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Exams 1939-1985, 2 folders (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Lectures 1940s (Box 8)
  - Bibliographies, circa 1960 (Box 8)
  - Course Sources-"Exercises in the Geography of Europe" 1946 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Courses (from a three-ring binder), no dates (Box 8)
- Reprints
  Also part of his academic career was writing, and here George Kish seemed to shine the brightest. His writings are represented in two series in the collection: Reprints and Manuscripts. The Reprints series contains some of Kish's writings, but by no means all of them. These are arranged first by publication, then by year in a "Miscellaneous" file.
  - Articles about G. Kish 1954, 1972, 1983 (Box 8)
  - Around the World Series 1960, 1962, 1967 (Box 8)
  - Geographical Review 1940s-1960s (Box 9)
  - Imago Mundi (various reprints) (Box 9)
  - Reprints (arranged by date)
    - Undated (Box 9)
    - 1936, 1940s-1980s, 7 folders (Box 9)
  - Reprints of encyclopedia articles (Box 9)
  - Book reviews 1960s-1980s (Box 9)
- Manuscripts
  Manuscripts consists of several files: "Books and Articles," "Encyclopedia Articles," "Speeches," "Television Scripts," "Unpublished," and "Notes." The first contains some manuscripts for books and journal articles that Kish wrote, showing changes in some of them. The "Speeches" file contains notes and transcripts of several speeches which Kish delivered, including one at the centennial of the National Geographic Society and the 1975 Henry Russel Lecture entitled "Image - Illustration - Instrument: the Map through History." During the 1950s and 1960s, Kish was involved in educational television, and the "Television Scripts" file represents the work that Kish did for educational television. (There are letters of praise scattered throughout the Correspondence section.) One box of the Kish materials was labeled "Unpublished Manuscripts" and all of these have been preserved under that same label.
  - Books and Articles
    - International Geographical Congress Proceedings, no date (Box 9)
    - Japan-Early Cartography of 15th Century, circa 1964 (Box 9)
    - Soviet Economic Atlas, circa 1967 (Box 9)
    - "Tibet au Coeur: La Vie de Sven Hedin", no date (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous Manuscripts
      - 1961, 1973, 1981-1989, 4 folders (Box 9)
      - Undated, 4 folders (Box 10)
  - Encyclopedia Articles undated, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Speeches
    - National Geographic Society Centennial Symposium-"Spirit of Exploration and Discovery: The Impact of Exploration" 1988 (Box 10)
    - Henry Russel Lecture-"Images-Illustration-Instrument: the Map through History" 1975 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous 1961-1981 (Box 10)
  - Television Scripts
    - "Families Around the World" 1955 (Box 10)
    - "Geography of Conflict" 1956 (Box 10)
    - "Hungary: One Nation Indivisible" 1957 (Box 10)
    - "The Glory That Is Italy" 1960-1961, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - "Russia: Faces of a Giant"-Notes for television series 1958 (Box 10)
  - Manuscripts labeled "Unpublished" 1939-1964, 1976-1983, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Notes for manuscripts 1940s (Box 10)
- Notes as a Student, circa 1930s
  The last two series are quite small, only comprising four folders total. The Notes as a Student are George Kish's notes from the Sorbonne in Paris and the University of Michigan. They are in French and English.
  - Three notebooks (Box 10)
  - Geography of Asia 1939-1940 (Box 10)
  - Unlabeled (Box 10)
- Photographs
  The Photographs are negative slide strips used as part of his 1975 Russel lecture on the history of maps; and photographs probably taken or collected while a Fulbright Visiting Professor to various universities in Italy, 1963-1964. There are no personal pictures of Kish and his family.
  - Russel Lecture Images (Negatives) 1975 (Box 10)
  - Italy (Negatives and Positives) undated (Box 10)
  - West Point lecture 1979 (Box 10)
- Miscellaneous
  - Correspondence and other papers, mainly dated from the last few months of his life in 1989 with correspondence of his wife and daughter, 1898-1990 (Box 11)
  - Audio cassettes (unidentified) (Box 11)
  - Notecards of lectures, etc (Box 11)